<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>It’s more than just overlap: text as graph</title>
  <!-- Verify that all items in bibliography are cited in body -->
  <!--
    rhd: There is one more thing that we might have to discuss: a lot of scholars when they 
    hear/read the word graph think of semantic networks. It is important to stress that a 
    text graph is not a semantic network. In the markup of an annotation layer it is of 
    course possible to link to persons, places, organisations, events etc in a semantic 
    network. The main point is that although a text graph and a semantic network are both 
    networks, and they can link to each other, there are not the same. I suspect the Balisage 
    crowd is more aware of this than the average  scholars but still. There are some Balisage 
    papers that advocate combining XML with semantic networks. A text graph approach is still 
    different from that approach. So maybe it would good to explicitly mention that to avoid 
    confusion.
  -->
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>The XML tree paradigm has several well-known limitations for document modeling and
        processing, some of which have received a lot of attention (especially overlap; see the
        overviews in <xref linkend="sperberg-huitfeldt_2000"/> and <xref linkend="derose_2004"/>)
        and some of which have received less (e.g., discontinuity, simultaneity, transposition,
        white space as crypto-overlap). Many of these have work-arounds, also well known, that—as is
        implicit in the term <quote>work-around</quote>—have disadvantages, but because they get the
        job done and because XML has a large user community with diverse levels of technological
        competence, it is difficult to overcome inertia and move to a technology that might offer a
        more comprehensive fit with the full range of document structures with which researchers
        need to interact both intellectually and programmatically. Proceeding from a high-level view
        of why XML has the limitations it has, this presentation explores how an alternative model
        of Text as Graph (TAG) might address these types of structures and tasks in a more natural
        and idiomatic way than is available within an XML paradigm.</para>
    </abstract>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Ronald</firstname>
        <othername>Haentjens</othername>
        <surname>Dekker</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para><!-- blurb about Ronald goes here --></para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle><!-- job title goes here--></jobtitle>
        <orgname>Huygens ING</orgname>
      </affiliation>
      <email>ronald.dekker@huygens.knaw.nl</email>
      <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
        >https://www.huygens.knaw.nl/dekker/</link>
    </author>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>David</firstname>
        <othername>J.</othername>
        <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
      </personname>
      <personblurb>
        <para>David J. Birnbaum is Professor and Chair of the Department of Slavic Languages and
          Literatures at the University of Pittsburgh. He has been involved in the study of
          electronic text technology since the mid-1980s, has delivered presentations at a variety
          of electronic text technology conferences, and has served on the board of the Association
          for Computers and the Humanities, the editorial board of <emphasis role="ital">Markup
            languages: Theory and practice</emphasis>, and the Text Encoding Initiative Council.
          Much of his electronic text work intersects with his research in medieval Slavic
          manuscript studies, but he also often writes about issues in the philosophy of
          markup.</para>
      </personblurb>
      <affiliation>
        <jobtitle>Professor and Chair</jobtitle>
        <orgname>Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, University of Pittsburgh</orgname>
      </affiliation>
      <email>djbpitt@gmail.com</email>
      <link xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new" xlink:actuate="onRequest"
        >http://www.obdurodon.org</link>
    </author>
    <keywordset role="author">
      <keyword>graph database</keyword>
      <keyword>TAG</keyword>
      <keyword>simultaneity</keyword>
      <keyword>overlap</keyword>
      <keyword>discontinuity</keyword>
      <keyword>mixed content</keyword>
      <keyword>white space</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </info>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>The XML tree paradigm has several well-known limitations for document modeling and
      processing, some of which have received a lot of attention (especially overlap; see the
      overviews in <xref linkend="sperberg-huitfeldt_2000"/> and <xref linkend="derose_2004"/>) and
      some of which have received less (e.g., discontinuity, simultaneity, transposition, white
      space as crypto-overlap). Many of these have work-arounds, also well known, that—as is
      implicit in the term <quote>work-around</quote>—have disadvantages, but because they get the
      job done and because XML has a large user community with diverse levels of technological
      competence, it is difficult to overcome inertia and move to a technology that might offer a
      more comprehensive fit with the full range of document structures with which researchers need
      to interact both intellectually and programmatically. Proceeding from a high-level view of why
      XML has the limitations it has, this presentation explores how an alternative model of Text as
      Graph (TAG) might address these types of structures and tasks in a more natural and idiomatic
      way than is available within an XML paradigm.</para>
    <para>From an informatic perspective all documents are structured, including those are
      traditionally identified as plain text. Some of the structural properties of plain-text
      documents are expressed through formatting conventions, such as the use of blank lines to
      separate paragraphs, or of indentation to mark the beginning of a paragraph, or of centering
      to mark a header. The sequence of words in a text, delimited in a complex way that involves
      white space, punctuation, and other symbols, constitutes, on a certain level, an
      organizational tier above the sequence of characters.<footnote>
        <para>Others properties, often more lexical than structural, may depend on contextual
          information that is not always expressed explicitly. For example, a capitalized reference
          to <quote>London</quote> is formally marked as a proper noun by capitalization, but
          whether it is a placename in England (or Ohio or Ontario or elsewhere) or the personal
          name of a US writer may not be represented formally.</para>
      </footnote> The conventions at work in plain text do not formally, completely, unambiguously,
      or in a wholly standardized way differentiate the content of a document from the coded
      representation of its structure (or, perhaps more accurately, structures), which complicates
      document processing (whether for data mining, publication, or other purposes). The challenge
      this poses has come to be addressed by representing the structural properties of a document
      not with plain-text characters (which might be considered pseudo-markup), but through
      standardized, formal markup, such as XML.</para>
    <para>The XML data model is a tree, or, more precisely, a rooted and ordered directed acyclic
      graph, which in the document-processing community has come to be known as an Ordered Hierarchy
      of Content Objects (OHCO). The OHCO model works well for describing structures that consist of
      single ordered hierarchies, such as the exhaustive tesselated division of a novel into
      chapters and the chapters into paragraphs. It is not well suited to structures that cannot be
      modeled fully as a single tree.<footnote>
        <para>The OHCO literature is already well known to the Balisage audience, and it is not our
          goal to provide an exhaustive bibliography. The seminal papers that advocated for OHCO as
          a document model are <xref linkend="coombs_1987"/> and <xref linkend="derose_1990"/>; the
          seminal examination of the limitations of OHCO, by some of the same authors, is <xref
            linkend="renear_1996"/> (first introduced as a conference presentation in 1992). Wendell
          Piez discusses issues pertaining to overlap and OHCO, and the alternative range model
          implemented in LMNL, in <xref linkend="piez_2014"/>.</para>
      </footnote> The markup community has focused intensively on overlapping hierarchies as a
      challenge to the OHCO model,<footnote>
        <para>Within the Balisage community, at present
            <link>http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/topics/Concurrent_Markup~Overlap.html</link>
          lists twenty-five presentations from 2008 through 2016</para>
      </footnote> and with good reason, but we argue below that overlap is only one manifestation of
      a higher-level problem, and this perspective has implications for deciding how best to
      overcome it. If overlap were <emphasis role="ital">the</emphasis> problem, projecting multiple
      trees over the content might solve it (e.g., through the SGML <emphasis role="bold"
        >CONCUR</emphasis> feature<footnote>
        <para>See, e.g., <xref linkend="hilbert_2005"/>.</para>
      </footnote>), as might the adoption of a model that permits but does not require hierarchy,
      including multiple hierarchies, such as the range model exemplified by LMNL.<footnote>
        <para>See especially <xref linkend="piez_2014"/>.</para>
      </footnote> But if the problem is that a tree is inadequate for higher-level reasons that are
      only partially exemplified by overlap, we might have more success if we address the issue at
      that higher level.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Desiderata for an improved text model</title>
    <para>The principal limitation of XML as a model of text is that text has structural properties
      that humans care about that cannot be modeled directly as a tree, or, at least, as a rooted
      and ordered directed acyclic graph constructed from the seven types of nodes that constitute
      the XQuery and XPath data model.[<xref linkend="xdm6"/>] Although overlap has received most of
      the attention, overlap is only one such challenge to XML modeling, and regarding overlap as
        <emphasis role="ital">the problem</emphasis>, instead of as <emphasis role="ital">a symptom
        of the problem</emphasis>, has led us to think narrowly about alternatives to OHCO. If what
      text <quote>really is</quote> is not an ordered hierarchy of content objects, what is it
      instead? The issues are well known to the XML community, so why have they come largely to be
      eclipsed by overlap in discussions of what’s difficult about modeling documents in XML? These
      challenges, which have largely been managed with workarounds in XML modeling and processing,
      find a natural solution in the TAG model described here, and are discussed in greater detail
      below.</para>
    <para>An improved text model should have the following properties: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>It should support both textual (character data) content and annotations (of the sort
            represented in XML through markup).</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Multiple layers of annotation should be possible. These layers may be created by a
            human (manually) or added by a computer using parsers, or through a combination of
            manual and automatic actions.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Overlapping annotations should be possible, as should discontinuous
            annotations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>It should make it possible to represent text that is not ordered without imposing an
            arbitrary order. It should also be possible to represent transpositions, or reorderings,
            e.g., in a critical text with variants.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Annotations on annotations should be
            possible.<!-- Give an example of why this is desirable --></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Hierarchical structures should be possible, but not required, and the system should
            permit multiple, partial, or overlapping hierarchies or annotations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to reading, the model should support queries for text, annotations, or
            a combination of the two.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to writing, the model should support creating, inserting, deleting, or
            otherwise modifying both textual content and annotations.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to workflow, it should be possible to defer decisions about relations
            among layers. For example, it should be possible to create annotations without hierarchy
            and apply a hierarchy only later. This deferral might be compared to the way XML
            documents may be validated against schemas that may be created and associated only after
            a fully functional well-formed document has been created.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to scalability, the model should enable, in a computationally efficient
            way, the types of documents and processing required by the digital text
            community.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to I/O, a system that implements the model should support serialization
            as plain text on export and the parsing of such serializations on import.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>With respect to user interaction, a system that implements the model should provide
            a legible interface that enables reading and writing by human users.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    <!--explain the differences between graph models and trees and ranges? Or leave that
        discussion out?-->
    <!--Reading Wendell his papers/articles about LMNL and Luminescent I can't help but notice
        that it is mainly about modelling text using LMNL, querying (using xLMNL and xQuery
        extensions) and visualising data. These are all read only operations. The goal of the TAG
        model and its implementation in Alexandria is that it can be used to read as well as write
        textual data and annotations. This opens up a lot of new possibilities and makes it a
        'complete' text repository system, comparable to XML databases albeit in a far more
        experimental state and a much lower level of maturity.-->
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The TAG/hypergraph model for text</title>
    <!--Describe the model. Think of it as sets. The fact that Alexandria is a read-write system
        is very important.-->
    <section>
      <title>About the TAG/hypergraph model and the Alexandria implementation</title>
      <para>This paper introduces the Alexandria text repository system, an open-source read/write
        implementation of the TAG model. It allows the user to import and store text files in either
        XML or LMNL markup, and it supports multiple layers of annotation that are permitted to
        overlap. The conceptual model behind Alexandria is a hypergraph for text as well as
        annotations.</para>
      <para>Graph models for text and markup have been proposed before (GODDAG [see, e.g., <xref
          linkend="sperberg-huitfeldt_2000"/>], GrAF [see, e.g., <xref linkend="ide_2007"/>]), but
        the model proposed in this paper differs from those because it incorporates a <emphasis
          role="bold">hypergraph</emphasis>. Hypergraphs differ from traditional graphs, which
        contain edges that connect only two nodes with each other. The edges in a hypergraph, on the
        other hand, can connect more than two nodes with one another, for that reason they are
        called <emphasis role="bold">hyperedges</emphasis>. Hypergraphs can have directed and
        undirected hyperedges. Undirected hyperedges contain a set of nodes. Directed hyperedges
        contain two sets of nodes, one for the source and one for the target. The direction of the
        (hyper)edge implies an order or a hierarchy of the nodes. Hypergraphs are especially
        valuable for text modeling because they can be implemented using sets. The data model
        consists of a number of node and edge objects of different types.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Nodes</title>
      <para>The node types supported by the model are: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Document nodes.</emphasis> Each document node represents a
              single document stored in the graph.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Text nodes.</emphasis> Text nodes present segments of text,
              comparable to <code>text()</code> nodes in a DOM tree.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Markup nodes.</emphasis> Markup nodes represent tags/markup
              present in the document.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Annotation nodes.</emphasis> Annotation nodes represent
              metadata on markup node. The model also allows for annotation nodes on annotation
              nodes.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Edges</title>
      <para>The edge types supported by the model are: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Document to text directed edges.</emphasis> A document to
              text directed edge connects a document node (source) with the first text node (target)
              contained in that document.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Text node to text node directed edges.</emphasis> The text
              nodes themselves are connected with directed edges, which order them, so that the
              linear order of the text is preserved.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Markup to text nodes directed hyperedges.</emphasis> Markup
              hyperedges connect the tags/markup nodes (source) to text nodes (target) tagged with
              the markup in question. Note that the use of directed hyperedges allows us to connect
                <emphasis role="ital">n</emphasis> markup nodes with one text node and vice
              versa.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Annotation to text directed edges.</emphasis> These connect
              annotation nodes to the first text node contained in that annotation. <quote>Text
                node</quote> contains the text of the annotation, not the original text.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">Annotation directed edges.</emphasis> These connect
              annotation nodes (source) with other annotation nodes (target), or they connect an
              annotation (source) with a markup/tag node (target).</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>How TAG addresses structures that are awkward for XML</title>
    <para>In this section we illustrate how three types of structures that are awkward for XML
      because they contradict the tree model can be represented and navigated in a natural way in
      TAG. For each we provide an abstract description of the problem, of one or more XML
      workarounds, and of the TAG approach, followed by examples drawn from use cases in Digital
      Humanities research projects.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Overlap</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Examples include enjambment and caesura in poetry,
          pages/paragraphs in prose, Frankenstein.</emphasis></para>
      <para>Adding a second or subsequent hierarchy is difficult, since XML markup syntax requires
        that the last opened tag is closed first. Adding the structure of the pages for example
        overlaps with the stucture of the chapters and paragraphs. This can be worked around by
        adding a second hierarchy as milestones instead of start and end elements.</para>
      <para>The problem here is that one hierarchy is handled differently from the second hierarchy.
        The leading hierarchy is modeled using full start and elements.</para>
      <para>Modeling multiple hierarchies is possible in XML, but difficult because the second or
        third etc hierarchy needs to be modelled differently from the first hierarchy. This also
        leads to challenges when querying or transforming the data contained in the file.</para>
      <para>There are many real use cases where there are multiple hierarchies present in the data:
        poetry, stage plays.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>White space as crypto-overlap</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Examples include caesura in poetry</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Discontinuity</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Examples include divided or interrupted speech in
          prose</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Simultaneity</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Examples include parallel readings in critical texts,
          simultaneous speech</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Transposition</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Examples include reordering across witnesses in criticial
          texts</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Comparison of TAG/hypergraph to other text models</title>
    <para>In this section we compare and contrast the TAG/hypergraph model with previous models for
      text processing, such as DOM (tree), GODDAG (graph), and LMNL (range).</para>
    <para>The document is written in a text serialization format, like XML or LMNL. It is then
      processed by a processor into memory model, like DOM. TAG is a replacement of DOM, competes
      with DOM, or with the Datamodel behind LMNL, based on ranges. NOTE: maybe a picture showing
      the use of XML markup to DOM and LMNL to TAG should be made to make clear what it is we are
      actually presenting here. The DOM (Document Object Model) is an API for XML processing. The
      alternative is XML Event processing. The DOM can contain both HTML and XML markup. The DOM
      contains a Node tree consisting of the following nodes: Document, DocumentType,
      DocumentFragment, Element, Text, ProcessingInstruction and Comment.</para>
    <section>
      <title>TAG and DOM</title>
      <para>Just like the DOM model the TAG model contains numerous types of nodes: TAG has a
        Document node, just like the Document Node in DOM. In the place of the Element nodes of the
        DOM comes the Markup node of the TAG model. Text nodes in the DOM model are part of the TAG
        model as well. NOTE: ProcessingInstruction and Comments are skipped for now in Alexandria,
        but could be added later. That is just an implementation detail.</para>
      <figure xml:id="XML_specs">
        <title>The XML document-processing ecosystem</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata format="png" fileref="xml-spec.png"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <caption>
          <para>Blah blah blah<!-- er ... change this --></para>
        </caption>
      </figure>
      <para>The difference between DOM and TAG lays in the way the nodes are laid out. The DOM model
        uses a tree based model, where there is a root node, which can have children, which are
        ordered sets. Every node can only have one parent node, and can only be child of one parent
        node. Thus representing a 1 to n relation between the parent and the childnodes. The TAG
        model uses a hypergraph instead, where nodes are connected through the use of hyperedges,
        allowing for n to n relations between text segments and markup nodes.</para>
      <para>In contrast with the DOM model there does not need to be a root element/node in the TAG
        model. A root node would simply be a markup node that is connected through a hyperedge with
        all the text nodes of the document. In fact there is no requirement to have a hierarchy at
        all.</para>
      <para>Also relations between markup nodes and text nodes or other markup nodes do not strictly
        have to be hierarchical. There can be multiple types of relationships between markup nodes.
        One of the differences with the DOM model is that the type of relation between the markup
        nodes can be deferred to a later stage. LMNL has the same idea, see the comparison with LMNl
        for more information.</para>
      <para>In the TAG hypergraph model de hyperedge that connects the text nodes with the markup
        nodes can be discontinuous. This is a clear difference with the DOM model, where all the
        text nodes are leaf nodes of the subtree underneath the element node. Thus the nodes
        underneath an element are continuous.</para>
      <para>The DOM and the TAG model agree on one thing, the fact that adding new text element or
        new markup is a local operation, there it differs from the LMNL model see the comparison
        with the LMNL model.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TAG and GODDAG</title>
      <para>The GODDAG datastructure allows for the storage of multiple hierarchies. Markup written
        in the MECS format can be parsed and read into memory. Elements that fully overlap are
        presumed to be dominating. Hierarchical structures are implied. Discontinuity is not
        supported. The graph is directed from the root node. The order of the text nodes is derived
        from the traversal of the element nodes. TAG differs in the sense that the order of text
        nodes is derived from explicit directed edges between the text segments. TAG differs in
        another way in the sense that relations between elements do not have to be one of
        domination. Relations between elements can be expressed by adding extra edges that are
        typed. The kind of relations can be determined later through the use of a schema. GODDAG and
        TAG are similar in the sense that they both support a N to N relation between elements
        (called markup in TAG) and PC-DATA nodes (called text nodes in TAG).</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TAG and LMNL</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: General comments about TAG and LMNL</emphasis></para>
      <section>
        <title>The LMNL and TAG data models</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO</emphasis></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>LMNL syntax in a TAG environment</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO</emphasis></para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>What LMNL syntax doesn't represent</title>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO:</emphasis> (apparently reserved for the limen, and not yet
          specified) that TAG requires</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Hypergraph versus ranges</title>
        <para>With the range conceptual model it is inexpensive to add extra annotation layers,
          however modifying the textual content is very expensive, since all the ranges of
          annotations that come after the point of insertion have to be recalculated. Hypergraph
          versus GODDAG: With the directed acyclic graph model it is inexpensive to add or change
          textual content, however since all the annotation nodes have to be connected to all the
          textual nodes involves this model scales badly with the number of textual nodes and the
          number of annotations. Hypergraph versus DOM: In the traditional tree model it is cheap to
          add or modify textual content and to add annotations, however there is only a single
          hierarchy. On top of that having a hierarchy is required. Scalability of the hypergraph
          model versus all the other models: In the hypergraph approach it is inexpensive (we really
          should use O notations here) to add or modify textual content, adding annotations is not
          as cheap as it is with ranges, (a new set needs to be created and a bit needs to be set
          for every text node involved), but it cheaper than the DAG model, since hypergraphs can be
          stored as sets rather than having to model individual edges.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Comparison of the hypergraph model with the LMNL markup file format</title>
        <para>A text graph representing all the data contained in a LMNL document consists of both a
          directed acyclic graph (DAG) and a hypergraph (HG). The DAG contains the range nodes, the
          annotation nodes, the edges between them, and all the text nodes and the edges between
          them. The HG contains all the hyperedges between the text nodes and the range nodes
          representing the many-to-many relation between them. That is, a text node has zero or more
          ranges on it, while a range can have zero or more text nodes associated with it. A range
          can be annotated, and an annotation can itself be annotated.</para>
        <para>The LMNL markup file format removes the constraint that the last opened has to be
          closed first. That means that it is possible to model overlapping hierarchies in LMNL. To
          be more precise, it is possible to model annotations with one hierarchy, multiple
          hierarchies or no hierarchy at all. This allows for a great freedom to model all kinds of
          information on textual content. This is great from a content perspective. However LMNL is
          more expensive from a computational perspective.</para>
        <para>LMNL data model LMNL documents contain text. Text can have ranges on them. Ranges can
          overlap. Ranges can be annotated on either the start tag or the end tag. Annotations can
          contain text themselves, that can have ranges, that can have annotations etc. Annotations
          can be annotated. Annotations on a range are ordered.</para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>LMNL conceptual model and how to map it to a hypergraph</title>
        <!--It is very important that we explain what we kept of the original data model behind
            LMNL and what we changed and why.-->
        <para>The conceptual datamodel behind is XML is the Document Object Model (DOM). The DOM
          represents a tree based data structure. The data model behind LMNL is different, in that
          it is based on ranges, based on offsets on textual content.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>TAG and linguistic corpora</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: Linguistic corpora are not recursive; there’s a single text
          stream</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>TAG in Alexandria</title>
    <!--some of this may be plans or projections, rather than implementation-->
    <section>
      <title>Introduction to Alexandria as a TAG implementation</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: write something</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Graph and hypergraph</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: write something</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Navigation and query</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: write something</emphasis></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Import and export</title>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">TODO: write something</emphasis></para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Example use case: tokenization with markup</title>
    <para>In natural language processing tokenization is the process of breaking a string of
      characters up into individual words. Tokenization is done using regular expressions. Regular
      expressions however only work on textual data and not on markup. (See the famous stackoverflow
      post for reference). On top of that the tokens themselves add another layer of information to
      file/model/data/document (not sure what the right word to use is here), which can overlap with
      the already existing hierarchy in the document. A data model for text that can handle multiple
      overlapping hierarchies or layers of annotations and that allows read as well as write
      operations can help out here. During tokenization all of the markup can be put 'aside' if it
      were and the tokenizer only pays attention to the textual content. The individual token are
      markup in a separate annotation layer. The existing markup layer are only ignored during
      tokenization, and still exist in the data.</para>
  </section>
  <bibliography>
    <title>Works cited</title>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="coombs_1987" xreflabel="Coombs et al. 1987">Coombs, James H., Allen H.
      Renear, and Steven J. DeRose. <quote>Markup systems and the future of scholarly text
        processing.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Communications of the association for computing machinery</emphasis>,
      30.11 (Nov. 1987): 933–47. doi:10.1145/32206.32209</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="derose_2004" xreflabel="DeRose 2004">DeRose, Steven J. <quote>Markup
        overlap: a review and a horse.</quote> Extreme Markup Languages 2004.
        <link>http://xml.coverpages.org/DeRoseEML2004.pdf</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="derose_1990" xreflabel="DeRose et al. 1990">DeRose, Steven J., David G.
      Durand, Elli Mylonas, and Allen H. Renear. <quote>What is text, really?</quote>, <emphasis
        role="ital">Journal of computing in higher education</emphasis>, 1.2 (1990): 3–26.
      doi:10.1007/BF02941632.
        <link>http://www.cip.ifi.lmu.de/~langeh/test/1990%20-%20DeRose%20-%20What%20is%20Text,%20really%3F.pdf</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="durusau" xreflabel="Durusau and O’Donnell 2002">Durusau, Patrick and
      Matthew Brook O’Donnell. <quote>JITTs (Just-In-Time-Trees)</quote>, presentation at New York
      XML SIG, January 2002. (Slides for <quote>Just-In-Time-Trees (JITTs): Next Step in the
        Evolution of Markup?</quote>, <emphasis role="ital">InterCharge: newsletter of the
        international SGML/XML users’ group</emphasis>, 8.4 (2002): 21–26.
        <link>http://www.durusau.net/publications/NY_xml_sig.pdf</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="erjavec_2007" xreflabel="Erjavec 2007">Erjavec, Tomaž. <quote>XML and
        overlapping hierarchies.</quote> Presentation at Tsujii Lab, Tokyo, 2007-09-01.
        <link>http://nl.ijs.si/et/talks/tsujiilab-crossing/crossing.pdf</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="hilbert_2005" xreflabel="Hilbert, Schonefeld, and Witt 2005">Hilbert,
      Mirco, Oliver Schonefeld, and Andreas Witt. <quote>Making CONCUR work.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Extreme Markup Languages</emphasis> 2005.
        <link>http://conferences.idealliance.org/extreme/html/2005/Witt01/EML2005Witt01.xml#Horse</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="ide_2007" xreflabel="Ide and Suderman 2007">Ide, Nancy and Keith Suderman.
        <quote>GrAF: a graph-based format for linguistic annotations.</quote> Proceedings of the
      Linguistic Annotation Workshop, held in conjunction with ACL 2007, Prague, June 28–29, 1–8.
        <link>https://www.cs.vassar.edu/~ide/papers/LAW.pdf</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="piez_2014" xreflabel="Piez 2014">Piez, Wendell. <quote>Hierarchies within
        range space: From LMNL to OHCO.</quote> Presented at <emphasis role="ital">Balisage: The
        Markup Conference 2014, Washington, DC, August 5 - 8, 2014.</emphasis> In <emphasis
        role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014. Balisage series on markup
        technologies,</emphasis> vol. 13 (2014). DOI: 10.4242/BalisageVol13.Piez01.
        <link>http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol13/html/Piez01/BalisageVol13-Piez01.html</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="piez_2015" xreflabel="Piez 2015">Wendell Piez, <quote>TEI in LMNL:
        implications for modeling</quote>, <emphasis role="ital">Journal of the Text Encoding
        Initiative</emphasis> [Online], Issue 8 | December 2014 - December 2015, Online since 21
      November 2015, connection on 08 March 2017. URL: <link>http://jtei.revues.org/1337</link>;
      DOI: 10.4000/jtei.1337.</bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="renear_1996" xreflabel="Renear, Mylonas, and Durand 1996">Renear, Allen H.,
      Elli Mylonas, and David G. Durand. <quote>Refining our notion of what text really is: the
        problem of overlapping hierarchies.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Research in humanities computing</emphasis>, ed. Nancy Ide and Susan
      Hockey. Oxford: Oxford University Press. 1996.
        <link>http://cds.library.brown.edu/resources/stg/monographs/ohco.html#derose</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="sperberg-huitfeldt_2000" xreflabel="Sperberg-McQueen and Huitfeldt 2000"
      >Sperberg-McQueen, C. M. and Claus Huitfeldt. <quote>GODDAG: a data structure for overlapping
        hierarchies.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Digital documents: systems and principles: 8th international conference
        on digital documents and electronic publishing, DDEP 2000, 5th international workshop on the
        principles of digital document processing, PODDP 2000, Munich, Germany, September 13–15,
        2000, revised papers</emphasis>, ed. Peter King and Ethan V. Munson. NY: Springer, 2004,
      139–60. A revised version is available at
      <link>http://cmsmcq.com/2000/poddp2000.html</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="sperberg-huitfeldt_2008" xreflabel="Sperberg-McQueen and Huitfeldt 2008"
      >Sperberg-McQueen, C. M. and Claus Huitfeldt. <quote>Markup Discontinued: Discontinuity in
        TexMecs, Goddag structures, and rabbit/duck grammars.</quote>
      <emphasis role="ital">Presented at Balisage: The Markup Conference 2008, Montréal, Canada,
        August 12 - 15, 2008.</emphasis> In <emphasis role="ital">Proceedings of Balisage: The
        Markup Conference 2008. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies</emphasis>, vol. 1 (2008).
      DOI: 10.4242/BalisageVol1.Sperberg-McQueen01.
        <link>http://www.balisage.net/Proceedings/vol1/html/Sperberg-McQueen01/BalisageVol1-Sperberg-McQueen01.html</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="xmlinfoset" xreflabel="XML InfoSet">XML Information Set (second edition).
        <link>https://www.w3.org/TR/xml-infoset/</link></bibliomixed>
    <bibliomixed xml:id="xdm6" xreflabel="XDM §6">XQuery and XPath Data Model 3.1. §6. Nodes.
        <link>https://www.w3.org/TR/xpath-datamodel-3/#Node</link></bibliomixed>
  </bibliography>
</article>
